{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In one battle in this year, Emory Upton used innovative assault column tactics to storm the Mule Shoe salient. In this year, an unsuccessful assault followed the detonation of underground explosives by Ambrose Burnside’s men in the Battle of the Crater. The Battle of Spotsylvania Court House occurred in this year, as did the Battle of Yellow Tavern, in which J.E.B. Stuart died. The Siege of Petersburg began in this year that saw the Battle of the Wilderness. Sherman’s March to the Sea took place in, for ten points, what year in which Lincoln was re-elected?",
      "answer": "1864"
    },
    {
      "question": "This period’s Shimotsuki Incident targeted the Adachi. Due to an earthquake, Sadaoki ordered his troops to purge his nominal superior at Heizen Gate. Kusunoki Masashige led forces in the Genko War during this period. In an attempt to reassert imperial authority during this period, Emperor Go-Toba started the Jokyu War against the Hojo regency. The ascension of Minamoto no Yoritomo started, for ten points, what period of Japanese history that succeeded the Heian?",
      "answer": "Kamakura period"
    },
    {
      "question": "One character in this novel is threatened with disinheritance after refusing John Brooke’s marriage proposal. While caring for the Hummel family, a musician in this novel dies of scarlet fever. A boy living next door to this novel’s protagonists marries the youngest of them after she returns from Europe; that boy is “Laurie” Laurence. This novel begins with its protagonists preparing for Christmas while their father serves in the Union Army. The series begun by this novel end by focusing on Fritz Bhaer’s wife in Jo’s Boys. For ten points, name this novel about the March sisters written by Louisa May Alcott.",
      "answer": "Little Women"
    },
    {
      "question": "The USS Charrette was given to this country’s navy and renamed the Velos, but its crew mutinied while docked at Fiumicino. Children were forcibly evacuated from communist controlled areas of this country and into camps run by Queen Frederica of Hanover. This country was ruled by the “Regime of the Colonels,” and the Enosis movement sought to unite Cyprus with this country. For ten points, name this Balkan country whose capital is Athens.",
      "answer": [
        "Greece",
        "Hellenic Republic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this group depicted his lover Hanna Fuchs-Robettin in his Lyric Suite, and another was accidentally killed by an American soldier shortly near the end of World War II. The founder of this group wrote a piece in which the narrator recalls living in the sewers of the title ghetto, A Survivor From Warsaw. This group developed a compositional technique that replaced traditional harmony with tone rows. Anton von Webern and Alban Berg were students in, for ten points, what early 20th century avant-garde “school” led by Arnold Schoenberg in an Austrian city?",
      "answer": [
        "Second Viennese School",
        "Second Vienna School"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This colony was home to a political family that included Henry Clay’s 1844 running mate. This state, the last north of the Mason-Dixon line to abolish slavery, was home to “Silk City,” the nickname for its city of Paterson. This state names a plan in which each state would have had a vote in Congress, contrasted with a plan named for Virginia. For ten points, name this state whose namesake college become the Ivy League’s Princeton University, and which also saw the Battle of Trenton.",
      "answer": "New Jersey"
    },
    {
      "question": "[Note:descriptionacceptable]Thiseventwasinspiredbyitsperformer’stimeataMagdaleneLaundry. A week after this event, Joe Pesci said that he would have “grabbed” this event’s performer “by her eyebrows.” It occurred during a live broadcast of a rendition of Bob Marley’s “War” and encouraged viewers to “fight the real enemy.” In its aftermath, the religious groups protested this event by using steamrollers to destroy records of songs like “Nothing Compares 2 U.” For ten points, name this 1992 incident in which an Irish singer desecrated an image of a religious leader on Saturday Night Live.",
      "answer": [
        "Sinead O’Connor ripping up a picture of the Pope John Paul II",
        "synonyms for “ripping” and “picture”"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This lake’s Mumbo Island is home to an eco-friendly resort. After a failed attempt to build a mission on Cape Maclear on this lake, one was successfully established at Livingstonia, named for the first European to discover this lake. This lake is home to over 500 species of fish that are divided into either the Mbuna or Peacock groups, the cichlids. For ten points, name this Rift Valley lake that shares its name with a nearby country with capital at Lilongwe.",
      "answer": [
        "Lake Malawi or",
        "Lake Nyasa"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The papal encyclical Mit Brennender Sorge condemned “with burning concern” the beliefs and policies of this government. This government punished prisoners in the “priest barracks” after it was criticized in a Christmas address. The Catholic Centre Party was dissolved after an agreement between Ludwig Kaas and Franz von Papen, who served as Vice Chancellor in the early years of this government. Pope Pius XII was controversially accused of ignoring, and therefore being complicit in the crimes of, for ten points, what government that perpetrated the Holocaust?",
      "answer": "Nazi Germany or the Third Reich"
    },
    {
      "question": "In April 2016, five police officers pled guilty to various charges associated with shootings on the Danziger Bridge during this event. During this event, The decision to not declare a state of emergency for Jefferson, and Plaquemines [PLAK-uh-meen] was later blamed on Governor Kathleen Blanco. Shortly afterbeingtold“You’redoingaheckofajob”afterthisevent,MichaelBrownwasfiredfromagovernment post. Refugees were trapped at the Superdome for several days after this event, which breached around 50 levees. For ten points, name this hurricane that devastated New Orleans in 2005.",
      "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After an October 2014 incident in this city, a Burger King surveillance video was supposedly erased before police reviewers were able to view it; in that incident, Jason Van Dyke was the only one of at least nine of this city’s officers to fire his weapon at a 17-year-old who had fallen after one shot. A year after that incident, after police video had been released, this city’s police Superintendent, Garry McCarthy, resigned, and Anita Alvarez was denied re-election as Cook County State’s Attorney. For ten points, name this American city where Laquan McDonald was killed.",
        "answer": "Chicago"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Chicago Police Department operates this “black site,” an interrogation warehouse where lawyers are denied access to their clients.",
        "answer": "Homan Square"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Spa Conference was held in response to poor coal deliveries required by this policy. This policy was nullified at the Lausanne Conference, which caused a de jure reversion to the Young Plan. Etienne Mantoux argued that this policy was justified in response to one scholar’s claim that this policy would lead to a “Carthaginian Peace.” Herbert Hoover issued a one-year moratorium on this policy, for which the Dawes Plan had attempted to find a solution for. For ten points, name this series of payments that were forced onto a defeated Central Power nation after World War I.",
        "answer": [
          "German reparation payments",
          "War Guilt",
          "descriptions of money that Germany owed after World War I"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "To enforce reparation payments, France and Belgium agreed to occupy what German industrial heartland, a river valley where German citizens responded with passive resistance?",
        "answer": "Ruhr valley"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Phrenologists noticed that bones of people from this civilization apparently exhibited Negroid facial features and argued that this civilization was visited by African traders, though less so in inland sites in the Tuxtla [toosh-t’lah] mountains. Archaeological sites of this civilization, like El Manati and San Lorenzo, show minor evidence of child sacrifice, collections of jade masks, and an “elongated man” style of figurine. For ten points, name this Mesoamerican civilization, claimed by Matthew Stirling to be the earliest, best known for its giant stone heads.",
        "answer": "Olmec civilization"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Olmec site in modern Tabasco, Mexico features the 100-foot-tall “Great Pyramid” complex and four massive heads.",
        "answer": "La Venta"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "According to Aristotle, this man bought all the olive oil presses in his city after predicting a good olive harvest. This philosopher’s students, including Anaximander and Anaximenes, belonged to a school of thought named after his hometown. That school of thought attempted to explain phenomena scientifically instead of through divine action. For ten points, name this pre-Socratic philosopher from Miletus who believed that the “first principle” of matter was water.",
        "answer": "Thales of Miletus"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Herodotus claims that Thales also foretold that one of these events would occur in 585 BC. That one of these events ended a battle between Lydian and Median forces near the Halys River.",
        "answer": "solar eclipse"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author wrote a poem about figures such as Hypermnestra, Medea, and Cleopatra in a work that essentially introduced iambic pentameter to his language. This author of The Legend of Good Women commemorated the death of Blanche of Lancaster, the wife of John of Gaunt, in his The Book of the Duchess. In one of his stories, Arcite and Palamon fight for the love of Emily, while in another, Alisoun describes how a rapist learns that what women want is to control their husbands. For ten points, name this author of “The Knight’s Tale” and “The Wife of Bath’s Tale,” two of his Canterbury Tales.",
        "answer": "Geoffrey Chaucer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The protagonists in the Canterbury Tales are visiting the death-site of Thomas a Becket, whose martyrdom is depicted in this T.S. Eliot play.",
        "answer": "Murder in the Cathedral"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A leader of this organization was nicknamed “The Artichoke King,” and some members of this organization were called “Mustache Pete.” Samuel Levine refused to work on Sabbath and led a Jewish section of this organization, whose command structure was damaged by the Commission Case. The Castellammarese War was a civil war fought between this organization’s Five Families that ended with The Night of the Sicilian Vespers. For ten points, name this Italian-rooted crime syndicate.",
        "answer": [
          "New York Mafia",
          "mob",
          "American Mafia"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Salaithos was executed for assisting Mytilene, a major port city on this Greek island. After a failed Mytilenian revolt, Athens divided this island’s land among Athenians, but let most of this island’s people live.",
        "answer": "Lesbos"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1622, John Brooke aboard the Tryall sighted Point Cloates on this island in 1622; the Tryall later became the first shipwreck in this island’s waters, near the Montebello Islands. One explorer suggested this island’s Kurnell Peninsula as a settlement site, but the first settlers to try it gave up after a week and moved to Port Jackson. Arthur Philip led 11 ships in the “First Fleet” to this island in 1787. James Cook landed at Botany Bay on the southeast shore of, for ten points, what Southern hemisphere island continent?",
        "answer": "Australia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The island of Tasmania was originally named by Abel Tasman in honor of this Dutch politician, who sponsored Tasman. The name changed in 1856.",
        "answer": "Anthony van Diemen or Van Diemen’s Land"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "John Farmer exposed Billy Hutchinson’s lies about being at this event. During this event, an ACARS message was sent reading “Plz confirm all is normal.” Thomas Burnett ended a phone call during this event with “Don’t worry, we’re going to do something.” This event concluded with Todd Beamer calling “Are you guys ready? Okay. Let’s roll!” as recorded on a black box. Ziad Jarrah led hijackers on, for ten points, which part of the 9/11 terrorist attacks that ended in a field in Pennsylvania?",
        "answer": "the hijacking of United Flight 93"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This detainee at Guantanamo Bay is considered the “architect” of the 9/11 attacks, having convinced Osama bin Laden to crash planes into specific targets.",
        "answer": "Khalid Sheikh Mohammed"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "19th century immigrants from this nation formed Turner Societies to bring to the U.S. a craze for gymnastics from their home country. Discrimination against Americans of this ethnicity led to Chicago’s Lager Beer Riot of 1855. One immigrant from this nation was Hayes’ Secretary of the Interior and also the first U.S. Senator born in this nation; that refugee from the March Revolution was named Carl Schurz. For ten points, name this ethnicity of immigrants who introduced to our country such customs as Christmas trees, hamburgers, and hot dogs.",
        "answer": "German-Americans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "German immigrant Carl Schurz was also a Civil War general, serving in this battle of October- November, 1863. Following Rosecrans’ defeat at Chickamauga, Grant drive Bragg out of Tennessee at this Union battle.",
        "answer": "Chattanooga Campaign or Battle of Chattanooga"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "GAY RIGHTS IN AMERICA",
      "prompt": "In the American gay rights movement, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "HIV-caused disease at the center of 1980s gay issues?",
          "answer": [
            "AIDS",
            "Acquired Immunodeficiency Syndrome"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "military policy for dealing with issues of homosexuality established by Bill Clinton?",
          "answer": "Don’t Ask, Don’t Tell or DADT"
        },
        {
          "question": "city in which Harvey Milk, self-proclaimed “Mayor of Castro Street”, became America’s first openly gay elected official?",
          "answer": "San Francisco, California"
        },
        {
          "question": "author of the opinion in Obergefell v. Hodges legalizing same-sex marriage, often considered a swing vote?",
          "answer": "Anthony Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "first state to legalize same-sex marriage in 2004 and represented by openly-gay Barney Frank in Congress?",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "woman who successfully sued to overturn the Defense of Marriage Act in 2013?",
          "answer": "Edith Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "early Communist-inspired gay rights organization founded by Harry Hay in the 1950s?",
          "answer": "Mattachine Society"
        },
        {
          "question": "umbrella organization that included that group and the Daughters of Bilitis?",
          "answer": [
            "NACHO",
            "North American Conference of Homophile Organizations MEDIEVAL JEWS"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Jews in the medieval world...",
      "prompt": "Name the jews in the medieval world......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "performed what financial service for Gentiles that brought outcries about “usury”?",
          "answer": [
            "lending money",
            "equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "were blamed for starting what 14th century epidemic of the bubonic plague?",
          "answer": "The Black Death"
        },
        {
          "question": "were expelled from Iberia along with what former controllers of Andalusia by Isabella?",
          "answer": "Moors or Muslims"
        },
        {
          "question": "were expelled from England by what king who conquered Wales and was called “Hammer of the Scots”?",
          "answer": "Edward I or Edward Longshanks"
        },
        {
          "question": "included what Sephardic author of the Mishneh Torah, a compilation of Judaic law?",
          "answer": [
            "Maimonides or Moshe ben Maimon",
            "Rambam"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "were victims of what belief that they processed fluid from children for ritual use?",
          "answer": "blood libel or blood accusation"
        },
        {
          "question": "converted leaders of what barbarian tribe southeast of the Kievan Rus who provided the nickname for Leo IV?",
          "answer": [
            "Khazars or Khazaria",
            "Khazar Khaganate"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "destroyed Axum under the leadership of Judith, a queen of what Abyssinian kingdom?",
          "answer": [
            "Kingdom of Semien",
            "Kingdom of Beta Israel AFRICAN BATTLES"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "From notable battles in African history, identify the...",
      "prompt": "Answer these questions about From notable battles in African history, identify the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "empire which successfully repulsed an Italian invasion in 1896 at Adowa under Menelik II.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "nation decisively defeated by the British at their capital in the Battle of Ulundi.",
          "answer": "Zulu"
        },
        {
          "question": "battle in which a French navy was defeated by Admiral Horatio Nelson at Aboukir Bay.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Nile"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War II battle in which Rommel’s Afrika Corps was defeated by Bernard Montgomery.",
          "answer": "Second Battle of El Alamein"
        },
        {
          "question": "battle in which the title city fell to the Mahdi’s army, who killed Charles “Chinese” Gordon.",
          "answer": "Battle of Khartoum"
        },
        {
          "question": "founder of the boy scouts who successfully withstood the Boer’s siege of Mafeking?",
          "answer": "Robert Baden-Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "battle where the revolt of ‘Urabi was successfully crushed, leading to the British occupation of Egypt.",
          "answer": "Battle of Tel-el Kebir"
        },
        {
          "question": "was where Lothar von Trotha decisively defeated the Herero, forcing them to escape through the Omaheke Desert.",
          "answer": "Battle of Waterberg"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) On the death of this man, the Richmond Enquirer wrote “[this man] was one of those patriots who fill a vast space in the nation’s eye.” As Speaker of the House in 1805, he became a leading figure of the Quids. Albert Gallatin wrote a bill that this man amended to (20 pts)",
        "expire with the end of the Congressional session, killing it. Despite his personal opposition, this man names a bill that gave the President the power to (10 pts)",
        "suspend trade with Britain and France. For ten points, name this early 19th century North Carolina politician who names two important foreign policy bills."
      ],
      "answer": "Nathaniel Macon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This phrase names a speech by Lord Palmerston that claimed all British subjects “shall feel confident that the watchful eye and strong arm of England will protect him against injustice and wrong.” in response to the Don Pacifico affair. It was first used by Cicero as the prosecuting lawyer against Gaius (20 pts)",
        "Verres, and was used by Saul of Tarsus to demand a fair trial in the Book of Acts. This phrase was called “the (10 pts)",
        "proudest boast” “two thousand years ago” by John F. Kennedy, who said that the modern day equivalent of this phrase was “Ich bin ein Berliner.” For ten points, give this Latin phrase that translates to “I am a Roman citizen.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "civis romanus sum phonetic,",
        "as from kids who know their classical Latin"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author continued Thucydides’ History of the Peloponnesian War in his Hellenica. Like Aristotle, this man wrote a well-regarded work discussing the constitution of the Spartans. This author’s comrades were victorious at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Cunaxa, though their commander was killed, and they cry out “Thalassa, Thalassa!” or “The Sea, the Sea!” after reaching the (10 pts)",
        "Black Sea. Despite its title, only the first chapter of this author’s best known work describes a journey inland to join Cyrus the Younger. For ten points, name this Greek who wrote about the Ten Thousand in his Anabasis."
      ],
      "answer": "Xenophon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One conflict with this tribe involved an attack on its Mikasuki branch at Fowltown, which was followed by the Scott Massacre. The Treaty of Moultrie Creek sought to place this tribe on a reservation. This tribe destroyed a force of 110 soldiers led by Francis L. (20 pts)",
        "Dade in the Dade Massacre. After the passage of the Indian Removal Act, this tribe refused to depart to Arkansas under the terms of the Treaty of (10 pts)",
        "Payne’s Landing. Thomas Jesup took advantage of a flag of truce to capture this tribe’s leader Osceola. For ten points, name this Native American tribe that fought three wars in Florida."
      ],
      "answer": "Seminoles"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The losing side in this battle retreated to a series of forts called the Quadrilateral. Ludwig von Benedek rose to prominence in this battle while defending San Martino, and this battle prompted the Armistice of (20 pts)",
        "Villafranca. This battle was the last in history to witness both sides being led into combat by their monarchs. Jean-Henri Dunant was present at this battle, which was so horrific it prompted him to lay the groundwork for the Geneva Convention and the International (10 pts)",
        "Red Cross. For ten points, name this 1859 battle in Lombardy, a victory for Napoleon III and Sardinia against Franz Joseph I’s Austrian empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Solferino"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One member of this family is last seen repeatedly shouting “It’s a lie!” to a “pitchfork senator.” Another member of this family buys a five cent glass of beer using a hundred dollar bill and is given ninety five cents back. That character is sent to prison and becomes a thief alongside Jack Duane, then an agent of the corrupt (20 pts)",
        "Mike Scully. The patriarch of this family loses his son, Antanas, when he drowns in the muddy street. That patriarch of this family is introduced at the beginning of the book as he marries (10 pts)",
        "Ona Lukoszaite at a bar in Packingtown. For ten points, name this family of Lithuanian immigrants whose patriarch Jurgis is the main character of Upton Sinclair’s The Jungle."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Rudkus",
        "Antanas Rudkus, Jurgis Rudkus,",
        "Ona Rudkus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After the second conviction of a member of this group, a nearby band played There’ll be a Hot Time in the Old Town Tonight. R.R. Bridges’ testimony expressed extreme doubt about the supposed crimes of this group. A.E. Hawkins declared a mistrial for one member of this group, (20 pts)",
        "Roy Wright, after the jury couldn’t decide on a sentence. This group’s convictions were overturned by the Supreme Court due to faulty (10 pts)",
        "procedures, including the use of a 100% white jury. For ten points, name this group of nine black youths whose case, in which they were convicted of raping two women on a train, went to the Supreme Court as Powell v. Alabama."
      ],
      "answer": "Scottsboro Boys"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The bones of one bishop of this city were “rediscovered” in a column by Vitale Faliero after the cathedral in which they were housed was destroyed in a fire. That saint’s body was hidden in a crate of rotting pork and cabbages to smuggle them past port customs in that saint’s (20 pts)",
        "translation from this city. Another saint from this city won a debate against 50 pagan scholars before Maxentius put her to death on a spiked (10 pts)",
        "wheel. For ten points, name this Egyptian city, home to St. Mark the Evangelist and St. Catherine, which once also held an important lighthouse and library."
      ],
      "answer": "Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Legitimists opposed this monarch in favor of Henri, duke of Bordeaux. In his early career, he had deserted to the Austrian army with Charles Dumouriez. This monarch ascended to power in the “Three Glorious Days”, and he survived an assassination attempt from Giuseppe (20 pts)",
        "Fieschi’s infernal machine. Public schooling greatly expanded under this monarch’s advisor Francis Guizot. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Orleanists was forced to abdicate in a 1848 revolution that placed Napoleon III on the throne. For ten points, name this French monarch known as the “Citizen King” who ruled during the July Monarchy."
      ],
      "answer": "Louis-Philippe I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s image descended from the clouds at the beginning of every national television broadcast in his country. Pierre Mulele was promised amnesty by this man, but this man castrated and executed Mulele for his role in the (20 pts)",
        "Simba Rebellion. This man paid $5 million to organize George Foreman and Muhammad Ali’s “Rumble in the Jungle.” This man overthrew his predecessor Joseph (10 pts)",
        "Kasavubu in 1965, after which he renamed his country Zaire. For ten points, name this leopard-skin hat enthusiast who stole billions of dollars as President of the Democratic Republic of the Congo."
      ],
      "answer": "Joseph Desir´e Mobutu Sese Seko Kuku Ngbendu Wa Za Banga"
    }
  ]
}